[SPEAKER_01]: A few years ago, you posted a video with the somewhat tongue-in-cheek title, How to Enter First Jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is often translated as something
[SPEAKER_01]: That can be entered upon.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, through a technique of meditation, method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, putting aside the Pāli inaccuracies, could you expand on why
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding entering upon jhāna is an inaccurate way of understanding jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, it's the implications of what entering means.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what's inaccurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I said it took how to enter jhāna factually.
[SPEAKER_02]: It wasn't like how to enter jhāna, boom, you can't enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, you can enter it, just not the way that's commonly presupposed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which is like I am entering jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is like...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm doing a meditation practice that then results in a special experience that will be jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also then, kind of, hand in hand with that, it's the assumption of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, I just go about my life and if I commit to these like meditation techniques and methods, I still have...
[SPEAKER_02]: I could still experience and have access to jhāna without, you know, having significantly uprooted centrality, unwholesome states, dwelling restrained, you know, with a gradual training in virtue and all of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then it becomes like a very kind of mystical type of esoteric practice of a special access to it taught by this monk or that monk through this method or that method.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you read the suttas, given the jhāna is from the suttas, you realize, yeah, sure, there is a method to jhāna, which is gradual training of withdrawal from the senses, seeing the danger in the slightest form, being watchful, knowing your intentions, not acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dwelling secluded and contemplating relinquishment, vāsāgā, left and right, to everything that's dear to you, then jhāna will be inevitable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But see, that's already nowhere near on the level of techniques and methods that people would assume, or people are taught, that jhāna is on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this idea of, like, a technique is, in a way, it's affirming the wrong order that... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, is the... You will not be able to engage in a technique without the wrong assumption, without the wrong assumption, the wrong order, I, wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, it is...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you're putting the hindrance first, this... Well, you're acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're acting out of it, exactly, which is...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I did another talk, jhāna is a lifestyle or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was like, jhāna... you don't enter jhāna, jhāna enters you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, but yeah, but there's also jhāna is a lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right, there's also... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm pretty sure there was another one because it was exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize, oh, you want to enter jhāna, your entire lifestyle needs to be that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, as I said in all of the other talks on the jhāna playlist and so on, it's just... You see, in the suttas, it's always the pleasure of seclusion from the unwholesome states arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you experience this sense of safety from all the unwholesome things that used to overwhelm you and control you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, after that, you enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind is composed in that jhāna experience, if you want to call it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But usually, even that assumption, it's like, you know, I enter jhāna, I enter this special experience, and then this tremendous pleasure arises as a result of that jhāna, because, see, first jhāna is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: No?
[SPEAKER_02]: The withdrawal from unwholesome states is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Safety from unwholesome states is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not like I enter jhāna and that pleasure withdraws me from unwholesome states and provides me with safety from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's upside down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, could another way of describing it be... so, you become established in what the Buddha would describe as mindfulness and then you... you direct that mindfulness more particularly or more specifically to, like, the first jhāna or the cessation?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: I suppose, in the broadest terms, that would be correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, you direct mindfulness can easily be taken as, okay, so now I'm doing this direction of mindfulness for the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: When your experience is fully purified from the five hindrances, from the craving, from the aversion, from the resisting of pain, from breaking of the virtue, from unworthfulness, from company,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You enter jhāna in a negative... in that negative way.
[SPEAKER_02]: By not doing certain things, your mind gets established and experience that sense of safety on account of unwholesome things that you stopped being bound by, and then you know, ah, okay, this is what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you think you can do something to enter jhāna, in that sense, or like, I tend to this and I change that, you're just doing it again with your own craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, it's a meditation with central principle, not without.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why, like, the whole idea of jhāna being the meditation experience should actually be completely abolished.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, again, as I said, it's not... in broader sense, it's not wrong, but in a practical sense, it always goes hand in hand with all these extremely wrong assumptions and mistakes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's... practically, it's better and safer to stop even regarding jhāna as any part of meditation experience, and focus on the gradual training of withdrawal from unwholesome states, seeing the danger in the slightest fall, being watchful, knowing your intentions, dwelling in seclusion,
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the signs of your mind, and then jhāna is the next thing, that you don't even have to want.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will have to happen, if you develop everything else rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've had people ask, like... That's why, sorry, it's often included as part of the gradual training towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, it's like a next step that will come on its own if you start developing gradual training correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mind will be composed in the right manner, the pleasure of safety will arise in the right manner, and you will know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I heard someone ask me, like, they do these ten-day silent retreats, where they sort of sit in a hall,
[SPEAKER_01]: And they say, like, I have no intention of speaking to anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's like, as if I'm alone, secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you describe why that isn't the case?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why actually, factually, you need to be... Well, the problem of that is because it's a ten-day retreat.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what have you been doing before the first day of the retreat?
[SPEAKER_02]: And what are you going to do after the tenth day of the retreat?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is your life, like, fully, you know, celibate, withdrawn from sensuality, day in, day out?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it just, you know, I'm trying my best and then I go on a retreat when everything is intense, but then I go back to my...
[SPEAKER_02]: There's that... Mahanāma, the the noble disciple, layman, he occurs throughout Majjhima Nikaya of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Talking about various things, and there was that sutta in the Buddha, that sutta in Majjhima Nikaya, where he says, how come the noble disciple who has understood the dhamma clearly, has seen the parallels of centrality, sometimes still centrality would come, and you forget all the dhamma you heard, and the mind is just obsessed with sensual desire, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the Buddha says, yeah, well, you know, for whoever has not experienced and developed that pleasure differently, the pleasure of senses, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: pleasure of jhāna on account of the gradual training,
[SPEAKER_02]: Their mind can still be attracted to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the in Chinese Agamas, there is a parallel, the same sutta, but actual description where the Buddha says whoever hasn't experienced this, it's changed, whereby it says whoever still lives with his wives,
[SPEAKER_02]: And that kind of ties in even better with another sutra, I think in Anguttara Incarnation...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I did a talk on it, where the Buddha says that the one who doesn't see
[SPEAKER_02]: Gratification, danger and the escape in regard to sensuality, the entire sensuality, that he can establish his mind in the first jhāna, such thing is not possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need to thoroughly withdraw yourself through seeing the peril of sensuality and then jhāna will come.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, as I said, more often than not, especially when it comes to these intense group retreats and so on, the idea is completely upside down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, my life still very much revolves around sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: I cannot even fathom or consider being completely celibate and giving all the sensual joy that I get from the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I just do these intense retreats and get this quick access to these higher states.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will then do the work of renunciation for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's just simply not how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: The importance to recognize that it's not an extension of a meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not a special novelty experience that arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: The unshakable mindfulness on account of full withdrawal from sensuality, because you've seen the peril of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Danger, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you feel you... See, if I recognize that I am
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, first of all, if you recognize the danger in itself, that you haven't been seeing before, that in itself already offers you a sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wow!
[SPEAKER_02]: This was so close to me, invisible all these years, and now I see it clearly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, just for that, you will be relieved.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let alone, now, you pursue that practice that goes even further from that, you know, sensuality that used to attract you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the safety, is seeing the danger, because you don't want something that's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't see it as dangerous, then... then you will just... you'll be attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The poisonous drink, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: The simile.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not... not recognizing that the poison is there, because it's not detectable through any of the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't smell it, you can't see it, you can't touch it, you can't hear it, you can't taste it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's another problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I must have done a talk on that as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of general meditation technique, that's concerned with observation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just the neutral, you know, like... how they call that... non-engaging, sort of... impersonal, just observe anything that comes and goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, again, is the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, again, you're observing that with your personality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't just assume the neutrality, when your experience is top to bottom, taken as mine, I am, impersonal.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why, like, this whole...
[SPEAKER_02]: Discernment of the poison becomes impossible, because poison is undetectable through your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can only be known once you've withdrawn from the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: But here you are, even your meditation technique revolves around furthering of your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Catching every single moment between your different observations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every single tactile sensation, every single thought, every single sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, touching, feeling, sitting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, absorbing yourself in the... where the problem isn't, even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eye can't see the eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thoughts can't access the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, so that's like the... that peril, the danger of centrality, needs to be discerned on that reflexive level.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you still expect jhāna and liberation from all the unwholesome states to come on the level of
[SPEAKER_02]: Technical and methodical observation of, like, whatever sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, in case of sensations, the entire domain of knowledge is shut.
[SPEAKER_01]: You switch it off.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're feeding the hindrances which you're trying to escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's still very much within.
[SPEAKER_02]: And some of these people might argue, yeah, but no, see, like, you know, the suttas talk about this and I still contemplate that.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the sutta contemplations and all the parallels that you might draw from the suttas and so on are secondary.
[SPEAKER_02]: To what you put first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what you put first is observations of my senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of touch, sensations, sense of whatever... sound, smell, taste, sights, perceptions of my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, all based on assumptions that you have a neutral access to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas in the suttas, the mindfulness, the order that this is encouraging is this yoniso, manasikāra... Yeah, as in the suttas, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't need to be observing every tactile sensation and every sort of thought that passes through your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: All you need to do is sustain the context of not acting towards the unwholesome ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Endure the pressure, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if it's not unwholesome, if it's not losing pressure, you can do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness is not
[SPEAKER_02]: Moment to moment, watchfulness of every second, mindfulness is not acting out of unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: The context that's developed on account of not acting out of wholesome states is what recollectiveness, right memory, correct recollection and right context is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, if all you are concerned with is observing sensations or nostrils or whatever technique you're doing, breathing in, breathing out, breathing in, breathing out, the intention behind all those actions is invisible to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there has to be a reason why you're doing those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why is it that you're observing sensations or trying to enter jhāna through a technique?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that so important to you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you know that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you see that it's not rooted in craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you see that it's not rooted in trying to either avoid pain or prolong the pressure?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is it rooted at?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's obviously, you know, if you look closely enough, you realize there is a degree of compulsion there.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a degree of, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is my technique.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is my method.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, you know, I've been doing this for so long.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, well, see, that's already a very unsuitable basis for entering jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is craving involved, if there is pressure involved, means there are hindrances involved.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if there are hindrances involved, there is no such thing as jhāna there for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can be true.
[SPEAKER_00]: I notice even
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if your technique is not as, sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know... Proliferated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Proliferated as those, but you're still doing it with that same attitude that you don't recognize why you're even doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, that's why, like the Buddha said, you know, in jhāna, that the pleasure of jhāna is not something you can crave for, before or after, or while you're in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there are no underlying tendencies, underline that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why that pleasure is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you enter jhāna by relinquishing craving, by relinquishing things you crave for, which, for most people who learn jhāna beforehand, would be relinquishing the idea of jhāna, relinquishing the idea of meditation technique leading to jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would bring you closer to jhāna than doing the technique towards jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: And once, yes, the mind abides in such relinquishing, relinquishment, withdrawn from unwholesome states,
[SPEAKER_02]: In seclusion, then, as the Buddha said, yeah, whatever, whether in that state, or first jhāna, or second jhāna, and so on, whether I walk, eat, go to toilet, extend my arm, whatever I do, it's divine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's outside of the domain of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's pure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you live in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: You abide in that jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's because you've relinquished the body that is the necessary basis for all of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the hindrances
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that obviously kind of, you know, calls for redefining hindrances of... statement hindrances affect the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know what you mean, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you have not surmounted the hindrances,
[SPEAKER_02]: Your idea of hindrances affecting the body would be very different than if you have surmounted the hindrances, and then you can say, yes, you know, hindrances apply to the body, but there's obviously a very different level of how affected the body is for somebody who is free from hindrances than somebody who isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where, in our last talk, we talked about authenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where it comes in, really, like seeing, is this rooted in craving?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like really being self-honest.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might catch yourself and you realize, okay, this is
[SPEAKER_02]: This is rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I'm here craving against these hindrances in order to re-establish myself in jhāna, which is why I'm within hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of my craving, not because of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't mean, okay, so I'll stop this.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means like, okay, no, I detected the mistake, so all I should do now is still strive to be free from hindrances, just minus my craving for being free from hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that brings us to that whole point that we often talk about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, so then you learn how to endure it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you endure it rightly, sufficiently enough, you will be free from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's your craving, while you're enduring things, whether you want it or not, it's your craving that interferes and obscures and blurs that picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you might endure things for decades, but if you endure with your craving that you're unaware of, that endurance will not bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you recognize, okay, yeah, endurance is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: However, craving is not necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can stop craving to, you know, either have jhāna or be free from this unwholesome state.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can just endure it without acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: By body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you free yourself from hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: And see, that's not underlined by craving now anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of that will be free from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the result of that is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the... because I really like the simile of... or the analogy of addiction, of being... kind of freeing yourself from addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know... is this... is this a useful analogy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you want to be free from the addiction of... addiction to cigarettes or whatever, it's not going to work if you sort of really just want the... the end results of kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to be, sort of, wanting to actually do the work of not giving in to continually smoking cigarettes.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you can't, sort of, expect to do something else that will then allow you to not be addicted to cigarettes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, theoretically, analogy is right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't give you the...
[SPEAKER_02]: Practically, what a person needs to see is, like, it's not enough
[SPEAKER_02]: When it comes to sensuality, to not just engage with sensuality physically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, in case of cigarettes, all you need to do is physically stop smoking it and then the body will detox itself and you will not crave for cigarettes anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, in case of sensuality, that same craving goes far beyond body.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's bodily, of course, but it's rooted in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you will need to not engage with the body when it comes to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will need to not engage with speech.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you need to be enduring it on the mental level, without acting out towards it, even by means of, like, distraction, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you endure it long enough on the mental level, without acting out towards it, one way or the other, that's how you will then uproot it in your mind as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what happens is, people would be withdrawn in the body, in the speech, but then mentally, they would feel justified then, in doing all sorts of things, including their practice, because they don't want to deal with that pure pain of saying no to sensuality, without replacing it or covering it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what happens when somebody, like, becomes sense-restrained and celibate, and then they start doing all this work and projects and seemingly meaningful and engaging in ideas and all of that to keep themselves occupied and floating, because if they stop distracting themselves in that engaging manner, externally wholesome manner, well, if they stop doing it, then internally they would feel the pain on that mental, and that's what you need to feel.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean, like, even practicing the dhamma, doing things, so to not deal with the pain, is not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dhamma is on the level of enduring it and not distracting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can even, like, I don't know, read a sutta about freedom from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or do a subha, subha, that's the common one.
[SPEAKER_02]: I must do a subha, I must do a subha, because I don't want to endure the pain of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, you must do a subha, but not at the expense of enduring the central pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, exactly, if you don't habitually just try to get rid of that pain of central pressure and sensuality, you can do a Supa at any given time within that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what Buddha said, you would be able, a monk who has developed his mind correctly, would be able to see ugly within beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or beautiful within ugly, or ugly within ugly, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Permutation, he sees it right there as it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: He wouldn't need to engage in a set of motions, techniques, and steps, and, you know, psychological methods to now replace this sensuality with a subha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, that's rooted in craving, and craving is the root of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, although you have nullified the currently attractive object of your sensuality,
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole framework of central pressure and pull and leaning towards those objects remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly what happened to the monks that did not develop yoniso, manasikāra sufficiently, and were trying to do this as subha, they ended up being attracted to corpses and and so on that Sutta has mentioned.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I keep saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: The most important thing is knowledge, clarity, honesty in regard to the intentions behind your actions, whatever those actions might be, body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, here we are.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a central pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, let me... let me spend next six hours reading the suttas and doing walking meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that it's bad, but it's not good either.
[SPEAKER_02]: Depends on why you do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you doing it so you don't have to feel the pain of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or are you doing it because you already saw the way out of sensuality and now you just want to fortify that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you think that just walking up and down and reading the suttas will magically give you a cure for sensuality?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or do you just think, oh, no, I just need some more information to know how to deal with this purely, without resisting it, kicking, screaming, or trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your intention will determine whether you're doing it rightly or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another word I've heard you use for intention is movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's helped me in the past, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, contemplate on the nature of intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: For example,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm speaking to you now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm choosing to speak to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is this sort of intentional intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why that is, yeah, I've used the word intentional intention, is because that choice is contained within a broader
[SPEAKER_01]: Intention, for example, of my heart beating, my brain functioning, my lungs breathing, that allow me to speak to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: A necessary basis for you in engaging, moving along those intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this yoniso, manasikāra, you talk about, eh... yeah, one way of, sort of, reflecting on one's intentions is, like, are my intentions causing me to ignore this broader context which... which, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It helps me to understand that, yeah, these choices I'm making, I don't own.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is, like, to recognize, like, of course, you can't, at the same time, to the same extent, think about the, you know, your current situation of beating heart, body here, any intention you're engaging with.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will take some attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, what is not inevitable, is you losing perspective, on account of choosing to act out of those intentions.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so, like now, you have a intention to ask me a question.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, yeah, maybe that intention is rooted because I'm restless, or because I don't want to be quiet, or because I'm curious, or because I'm bored.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, obviously, in this case, or because I want to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either of those ways will be engaging, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: And...
[SPEAKER_02]: But as long as you now know, okay, but see, if I'm if I am asking it because I want to know, the answer can then shed more light for the future practice and context.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that case, like pursuit of information is wholesome, because it can help you then eventually stop depending on external information.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sometimes people kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, get the sense of that, but then, too soon, they stop asking questions, because I mustn't ask questions, there will just be information and intellectual knowledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, you need to know what you're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, you will be engaged, and to that extent, you will lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, see, this course of action, loss of perspective, can then result in broadening perspective later on, because now you know what to look for, you will know what to notice, you might then notice it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Going a different course of action, of not asking questions, or asking questions for wrong reasons, and not paying attention to it, well, again, that's also distracting itself, but then, in the future as well, will perpetuate the distraction, and it will not broaden the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it comes down to, yeah, why do I, like, why do I want to do this?
[SPEAKER_02]: And often, like, people might be asking me questions on dhamma, but then they keep asking the same thing every time we meet.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, it's obviously apparent to me, but it might not still be apparent to them that, well, you're not doing this for the right reasons anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just repeating the same thing because you need emotional conviction.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need emotional kind of reassurance.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are not merely seeking information on account of which to practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want me to reassure you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if I say things you want to hear, it's your own mind that's making you insecure and doubtful, which means it's going to last only for a period of time before it comes back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, yes, initially, the questions might have been rooted in really wanting to learn, but then that got obscured for yourself, and now your questions are rooted just in trying to rekindle that inspiration on account of very wise words that you heard externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Using you as some kind of pillar of strength.
[SPEAKER_02]: And like, yeah, you might do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not necessarily an immediate clear-cut, but sooner or later, you will know clearly what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's then when it comes down to, okay, so now, are you consciously, volitionally, choosing to perpetuate it, or are you trying to put a stop to it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you acting out of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's when the kind of choice of practicing the dhamma is brought back down onto you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is the opportunity of seeing anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the opportunity of like converging in the right direction and reinforcing the right direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's entirely up to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, I missed the chance or I slipped there.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't see this.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always on the level of a very conscious choice that you, when you become aware of it, decide to either ignore or do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This also brings me back to the question I asked earlier on about... it's like sitting in a hall full of people, because I used to do that a lot, and there was always this sense of... this might be a bit off-topic, but the sense of there being this collective responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're doing this, like, you know, together.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, you got to abandon that long, long before you even start.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why seclusion is so important, being alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Individual responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but being alone...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mentally, I think, as well, as in not... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being alone with your own choices and recognizing there is no collective group here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you're sort of engaging with somebody, asking questions or... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You still realize where the emphasis is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to be doing it ultimately in order to be not needing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you kind of end up wanting to do... What you described, that often happens in the monasteries as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Monks develop this notion of we are in this together, type of thing, and it's it's it's absolutely laughable in a way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, from the authenticity point of view, thinking we are doing this together, it's just, what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, I was saying that in some other context, you know, like the the assembly of arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not an assembly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a group of individuals.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an external group of every single individual for himself.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's the purest assembly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no sense of projected identity in the group.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of inauthenticity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of, oh, it's easier for me to do this if everybody else around me is doing this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that can be a factual kind of motive to start with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get reminded of what you're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't see a problem with that, it means you're never going to grow out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means you will need, then, everybody else to keep doing the same thing, so you keep your peace of mind intact.
[SPEAKER_02]: If one person steps out of the line, you will be existentially challenged, because it reminds you of the fact that, yeah, we are all doing the same now, but at any given moment, any given person can choose to do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that then means, oh, but then...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can choose to do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means I'm not in control of this, you know, heavily controlled mind otherwise, and the environment and circumstances and the rules and observances that we all adhere to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, there you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your peace went out of the window.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the owner of my actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Alone with my actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there's nothing and no one can come between you and your actions.